howdy this is jim rutt and this is the
jim rutt show
[Music]
listeners have asked us to provide
pointers some of the resources we talk
about on the show
we now have links to books and articles
referenced in recent podcasts that are
available on our website
we also offer full transcripts go to
jimrutshow.com
that's jimrutsshow.com
today's guests are ferran de ibarra
and art brock of commons engine and the
holochain
project fernanda is director of the
commons engine
she's a visionary social innovator and
regenerative
entrepreneur bringing over 15 years of
experience with community building
and currency design art has worked to
unlock the secrets of the social dna by
which people operate
and the critical role of currencies for
programming these
patterns art builds targeted currencies
which shape the social dynamics of our
emerging post-industrial economy he's
created more than 100 designs for
multi-currency systems and this software
company has built and deployed
dozens of those systems so we're going
to talk about
currencies today in a quite general
sense
and it would be quite interesting
conversation
i had a previous podcast with
art it was episode 56 on may 28th where
we went in great detail
into art and fernanda's holochain
project for people who want specifics
about holochain
i would point up to that episode it may
well come up in the conversation today
but the focus today
is going to be on currencies more
generally so let's start with exactly
that
when we're talking about currencies in
the most general
sense i mean as general as you can make
it how would we define
currency either one of you feel free to
take that question
well i i know i have a very specific
definition
where i where i'm trying to let me just
start
off by saying we use the word currency
and money rather interchangeably in
english
and i don't money to me is
a particular type of currency it's a
medium of exchange currency i'm trying
to reclaim the word currency
more in in resonance with its original
roots from the latin query to run to
flow
right like electrical currents and river
currents and and things like that
in fact there's a mnemonic that i try to
give
people to remember when i use the word
currency think of it like
currents dash c like c
with your eyes the ability to see flows
to see
currents so my very specific definition
is that a currency is a formal shared
symbol system that we use
to shape enable and measure flows or
currents
and you can see how money is a type of
symbol system
that we use to shape enable and flow
exchanges of goods and services
right but there's many other kinds of
flows that money isn't very good at
right like uh sharing caring trust
attention
those kinds of things and so when you
understand the word currency in this
broader
context and yet a formalized context
still
it gives you access to shaping these
flows very powerfully
very interesting fernanda do you have
something to add to that
indeed well as arthur said he has been
using that definition of currencies for
a long long time
and been with him working for decades
the part that got me into adopting that
definition but not only adopting but
that actually gave me
more tools to think about systems
because when i see
i started to see flows and i started to
see currencies
everywhere so it's like a little switch
and sometimes uh we call it like the red
pill versus the blue pill
moment and once you have it and once you
get it
you start seeing life i mean
and if you sit in or with how living
systems work
that they work because of the flows and
the relationship
among the objects then it makes total
sense to be able to
see current seas
to track currents that would be my
two bytes on that jim well very good
i will confess when i tend to use
currency i use it more abstractly than
the average person in the street but
considerably
less broadly than y'all do my definition
i call it signaling systems for the
coordination of production
investment and consumption which allows
us to get
pretty far afield but still keeps us in
what is
at least approximately the monetary
domain
so many of my questions and examples are
more likely to come from that space but
i would encourage you guys to take it as
general as you would care to because
i think both myself and our audience
would love to learn about this
broader perspective and i do think
that's very important whenever i talk
about
currencies one of the first things i
have to do with
a audience is that unfortunately
particularly in places like the united
states people have reified the concept
of
money and you know as i like to say the
first job is to convince people that
money or currency in this sense of
coordination production investment and
consumption
didn't come down from mount sinai with
moses
right it's a series of frozen accidents
it's a
series of institutional designs
essentially that happened over time for
various reasons created by humans and is
constantly in flux i mean
even our current money system underwent
a fairly major change in 1971
as late in the day 1971 where we finally
went off the gold standard and
one could argue that the innovations
after the 2008
financial crisis represented another
major change
and so i always like to start the
conversation by
whether we define it relatively narrowly
or relatively broadly
that currencies are social institutions
created by humans
subject to change and subject to
development to better serve needs for
human well-being
why don't one of you guys give the
audience an example of a currency
that is outside the production
investment and consumption
space just so we can get a sense of the
breadth of your definition
there's a definition that i lean sorry
there's an example that i lean on
because everybody's pretty familiar with
it
of non-monetary currencies and it's the
currencies we use in education
right so a college degree is a kind of
reputation currency that is reputing
that you've attained a certain level of
learning in a particular field
you know if you want to build a bridge
it's
good to have somebody that has been
certified as a structural engineer
you know involved in this project and
there's a bunch of people who have
certified that they've reached a
particular
level of learning in this field so your
bridge is not likely to break right you
know
it's very useful to have that kind of
reputational
dimension and ways of managing that of
hiring for that that kind of thing right
but that's not the only currency right
and we
also use credits for example because you
get the degree by getting you know
25 credits of this and 12 credits of
that and 15 credits of the other thing
and
credits are just a unit of account
currency counting your course hours
in different domains of work required to
fulfill the degree
but the credits only count if you get a
good enough grade and the grades
are a performance metric currency
attempting to measure how well you're
learning
the content of the course none of those
are monetary currencies like you may pay
the school
in a monetary currency for being
enrolled and taking the classes
but these are other currencies that
shape the flows of participation of
students
yeah and and then sort of your balance
sheet in that story is is your
transcript
right it shows you the status it's sort
of like the scoreboard of
where you are in acquiring the stacks of
credits you need and
the grades that you've gotten and you
divide up power
in that space by who issues which
currencies professors issue the grades
departments issue the credits
the university issues the degree so do
you get what i mean by
this is a thing that shapes the flow
millions
of people's participation in education
yeah it would certainly fall into my
broader bucket of coordination of
production investment and consumption
because it's around the production of
education
and then later it's used to shape job
opportunities in
the areas of work which then leads to
consumption etc so i can see how that
falls even into my somewhat narrower
definition
than your very broad definition though i
would point out
this is another subdivision i discovered
many years ago
and i believe you also use this
distinction which is a distinction
between
transactional type currencies like
money systems and static ones like or
relatively static ones that are not
transactional like reputation systems
and i think that's a very important
distinction to make because you don't
for instance you cannot
spend your college credits right in fact
that would be some form of fraud if you
somehow
you know manage to transfer your college
credits to me
that would not be the purpose for this
particular kind of social signal so
is it worth distinguishing that
dimension most definitely
a good reputation currency should not be
able to be transferred i
have a blog post actually about this
that reputation and exchange are
orthogonal
dimensions of design in a currency right
you
and and when people make reputation
currencies that can be traded
they're almost always really crappy
reputation currency designs
if you can buy reputation or if you lose
reputation
because you're actually leveraging it
right it's not that you didn't do the
work that was reputed it's not that you
didn't acquire the learning
right when you get into you use your
high school degree to get into college
but
they don't own your high school degree
when that happened you didn't lose your
high school degree
right so the reputation
still needs to remain for it to have
integrity still needs to remain with
the person that earned that reputation
for what they earned it for not for
buying it or something like that
but the credits are an interesting
hybrid right because credits can be
transferred if you transfer to another
university
and part of what you're trying to look
at when you transfer to another
university in fact is
how well will my credits transfer how
well where the will the work that i've
already done
transfer in and count toward work toward
a degree in this other university
now they don't transfer to another
person right but so there there are
there are always rules in the
transactional dimension
that place constraints and sometimes
they just can't be
reassigned to another person but
sometimes they can still be
accepted by another organization in in
their
accounting i'm going to be a little bit
nerdy here i'm going to suggest
that moving you know the transfer of
credits is actually more like
it's something different because it
doesn't actually disappear from the home
institution either so let's i move my
credits from you know arizona state to
arizona university i actually have
credits at both places in fact it's
probably more like some kind of foreign
exchange
transaction where somehow my arizona
state credits
turn into arizona credits but they still
remain arizona state credits as well so
there's something
interesting and slippery about that
particular example
well for me if we follow the track of
education and currencies
what i'm interested about i mean i'm a
self-instructed learner
since forever and i raised a girl
that was on and off from school during
her
whole life she's 19 now but at for 13
she opened her first maker space and she
figured out
that the slower learners were those kids
that were coming out of school
and then she started to figure out how
am i going to do this without
without having the credits from school i
really don't want to go to school
but how can i prove all that i know
right she has studied about
finances and learning about marketing
and she has learned how to
make a startup and how to raise funds
and how to do crowdfunding and
by the time if she would want to study
business by the time that she would be
actually
interested in something that she would
be
passionate about learning it would take
a long time
for other students to catch up so what
are the currencies of the future that
will show
us when someone has gone through a
certain flow of skill education
performance
knowledge you know coordination with
others collective intelligence i mean
you name it
that will help us and enable us to move
and evolve what we know now as the
educational system or the way
of showing that we know because right
now it's like if the
universities were the bank and they're
the ones like the
issue the currency and if you don't have
the currency
you don't have a phd you know you can
get
a job but the phd person will always be
regarded as different than the one that
doesn't and i believe that my whole life
except when i already had sufficient
reputation nobody really cared
interesting yeah i've certainly played
that game having been a person engaged
in the sciences
without a phd you definitely have to go
quite a bit further down the road to
prove to people that you're able to play
the game at their level
and at least in that domain i'm not
really aware of an alternative
signaling system other than just
demonstrating it by doing the work and
being able to hang with the big dogs
but certainly that would seem to be a
very significant opportunity there you
know you look at the
300 000 to get a four-year university
degree from an elite university
most of the interesting work seems to
show that the actual amount of
things learned in undergraduate
university in the united states at least
is relatively
little in fact i had very interesting
guest jason brennan
on the show back in december i think in
his new book
cracks in the ivory tower he makes a
very
strong argument that most of what goes
on in universities is actually
signaling as well as opposed to
substance you know the students
cynically
take the easiest courses for the highest
grades the professors
modify their teaching to get high
student evaluations
the administration is always interested
in more administration and more tuition
etc
so you know the university game itself
is all caught up in signaling
but it presumably opens an opportunity
to do exactly what you were talking
about with your daughter
fernanda a way for her to be able to
demonstrate in a transferable way that's
the interesting part that gets us back
into currency design
in a way that's more or less fungible
that you can prove
that this person is sort of equivalent
to that person
through some other mechanism than
spending three hundred thousand dollars
and four years of your life on
relatively unproductive work
i think that's an area there's gonna be
a lot of interesting things going on
thinking about you know things that are
actually happening in that space it's
very light
but linkedin has you know has their
endorsements
thing which is kind of a weak version of
that where you know oh this person's a
good leader or this person's good at
project management etc and your contacts
on linkedin endorse you
and sometimes i'll write a little word
or two about you and
i suppose that's mildly interesting i
don't know to what degree employers
use such things but there certainly
would appear to be some real
opportunities to
make those signals you know more more
truly meaningful where you actually
could use them to get a job
well i don't know i mean it depends
right if you have
something that like a portfolio of
things have you done
and reputation with people and
then you start getting in your way in
what you
can do and what is possible but that
probably it's another variant another
path that we can take in the
conversation so i don't want to deviate
it from our currency topic
that is for sure something that we want
to be able to see
on what possible designs are there
in the future so that the the issuance
of knowledge doesn't belong to the
universities alone
yeah one example from history is the
guild systems
where essentially the guilds took on
responsibility if you were a
silversmith for instance you'd start as
a junior apprentice then you'd be an
apprentice then a senior apprentice and
a journeyman and then a master
eventually
and those actually had very significant
meaning that were transferable across
at least western european medieval
systems
so if you were a master silversmith in
france it meant about the same thing
in germany and you could move to germany
and get a job as a master silversmith
so there's at least one example where
that can become transferable
and that's probably where we get back to
our discussion of currencies
where the signal isn't idiosyncratic
like a portfolio
but rather has relatively simple surface
attributes
you know for instance a ranking system
within a guild
if that makes any sense arthur i think
looks like you have something to say
about this
yeah it's interesting because like the
transfer of credits
isn't a standard double entry accounting
transaction right you don't
the the source isn't debited for the
credits and that's generally true of
reputation currencies
the source isn't debited for having
reputed something so you were talking
about those linkedin
endorsements where you know i say you're
good at podcasting or you're good at
science or you're good at you know
systems thinking or whatever the
the thing is right i'm not being debited
anything for saying those things but
there's some interesting language that
we use sometimes around this that i
think gives us a clue as to really what
is going on
where we talk about lending credibility
to something so like i'm not actually
being
debited for it but if you have the
system working right
i should be on the line in some way if
i'm saying
this is a good person hire them
and they're not then that should come
back to reflect
on me in terms of my reliability of
recommendations
right so it's not like i'm being debited
but
if there's nothing that i'm on the hook
for then you have a pretty wishy-washy
reputation currency
because my reputation for being able to
discern
somebody's character or somebody's
skills and you know and be able to make
a good recommendation
at the very least should be on the line
so that's interesting
so we talk about a signaling system
there needs to be a back channel
essentially that all right i employer
relied upon your signal turned out your
signal was bad
there needs to be a way to send a return
message back to your reputation that
says
at least with respect to this
transaction your signaling was of low
quality
something like that that's right and and
boost it
if it was of high quality so people who
are really great at making
recommendations and placements
they get listened to more and people
that are not so great about that
get less than two less yeah it'd be
great to hook that into
a rating system on social media right
because unfortunately a like is a like
as a like or a retweet is a retweet is a
retweet
and if one could somehow have feedback
on the quality of those recommendations
and filter them and down regulate them
or up regulate them based on your
previous
experience with that particular signaler
that would be quite useful
yes indeed it also reminds me in the
currency
the mutual credit i implemented in
mexico it is called leanness and still
going
and one of the ways in which people get
into the circle
of the mutual credit of olines uh
is through someone's recommending you
actually the only way
and that person has to be responsible
for your learning
and has is kind of some sort of body
system
where they go with you until they're
sure that you can walk on your own you
know the system you know how to transact
you actually
it's pretty intense when you do it into
mutual credit because it's not
money it's community currency so you
don't do what you can do with money
and people we are so used to
just transacting with money that we
forget about all
other dimensions of value that can be
shared within a community context
and then we need to learn those things
as well so the body system works that
way
and it's really useful sometimes you
would have somebody that would say hey
i'm new to town
and i heard about rolliness and i would
like to be part of it
and then you will allow them to have a
certain
credit limit until they prove their
reputation
by the number of transactions they have
other number of
happy people with a way in which they
provided value to the community and
things like that
but i would always have wanted to see a
system that would integrate
that reputation currency with a mutual
credit even at time banks
so you can see different dimensions as
arthur was saying because it's not
linear or flat like you can have two
carpenters that are awesome
and joe is fast and he's not that
expensive
but his things don't tend to last many
years
while you know joe he's very slow but
his quality is amazing and he's very
likely
that his furniture would last for
hundreds of years
and then both are not good or bad it's
just about what is the choices that you
want to make
and be able to make those dimensions
visible
so that people can make informed
decisions
when you want they want to be able to do
a transaction
based on what your reputation looks like
but most of the systems are pretty flat
so you don't really
see dimensions
yeah i guess the question is does it
cognitively map to what humans are
actually capable of dealing with
and it is always important i point this
out to people who
like myself enjoy designing these
systems is that 50
of your audience if this is a global
system will have an iq less than a
hundred
so it's important to design a system
that's actually tractable with the
actual human cognitive ability
you'll find on the ground yeah what's
interesting about that though is i think
people have more capacity in this domain
than we give them credit for
at least in the domain of what i call
currencies i think we navigate
different we re we navigate you know
dozens of different currencies a day
and understand by context which set of
rules we're operating in
so that you don't try to use your grade
on your math test to
pay for gas at the gas station you don't
use a postage stamp for
or your or your bus pass or your you
know like there's lots of different
kinds of currencies
that make sense in certain contexts and
but i think what you're pointing to
is that the currency has to map well
to the social frame to the social
expectations if it doesn't map well
then you're going to cause too much
cognitive overhead
of trying to like have people remap ah
very well said i like that
yeah but there's different social
contexts in which there's different
social frames
right so when when i go across the
street
and you know to my neighbor brian and i
say hey
can i borrow a handful of nails i'm
working on this project and i've run out
of nails i just want to be able to
finish this project
man he would like root through his
basement for an hour to find me that
handful of nails or something like that
he's like
excited to help out and and he doesn't
want me to
hand him a couple bucks for the nails he
gives me he doesn't want me to go
you know next week when i've gone to the
to the hardware store and to return some
nails to him or anything like that
it's not an exchange type of social
contract
what it is in this case is a is
neighbors investing
in living in a neighborhood where
neighbors treat each other well
right and so if you make your reputation
type of currencies
map to that frame then they have low
cognitive overhead
but if you start trying to make them
really complicated with a bunch of other
rules you're trying to push in there
then they get complex and they they take
a lot of cognitive overhead
i think that's a beautiful distinction
very well said in fact i act i grew up
in one of those neighborhoods of
call it upper working class lower middle
class you know plumbers electricians
carpenters
cops what have you and the whole
neighborhood basically ran on a kind of
loose form of reciprocity
i never heard of anybody ever actually
calling a plumber somewhere
in the neighborhood there was always
someone that knew enough about soldering
and piping and what have you to be able
to
instruct you on how to fix your sink or
unstuck a toilet etc
and they'd expect you to reciprocate but
not one-on-one and not necessarily now
was kind of a very loose unstructured
form
of reciprocity credit that built up over
time
and i don't know if that actually falls
into our definition of currency but it
certainly falls into the
signaling system domain yeah what's
really interesting about it though is i
think you have to be careful about the
reciprocity piece because it lets you
still
hold on to that money concept where
there is a little bit of a tit for tat
exchange
going on because what's really
interesting is if i go borrow that
handful of nails from brian and he finds
it pretty easily and i thank him and i'm
grateful and you know that kind of thing
what what's actually been invested in is
our relationship
and it actually increases my ability to
go back to him next week and say
hey man can i borrow your lawn mower i
can't get mine to start
or whatever right it's not it's not that
now i owe
him an equal measure it's that we're
investing in the
neighborliness and both of our abilities
to use that neighborliness go up
when we do that yeah that's interesting
because that gets around the classic
western
point of view failure of seeing the
objects but not seeing the relationships
so in this case if you argue that what
you're doing is investing in the line
that connects the two
objects rather than either of the two
objects that provides a different
framing for thinking about the problem
yes and it also points to another aspect
that we
constantly emphasize about not wanting
to track
absolutely everything because then i
mean if you wanted to track that and
then oh
i'll go to our inter our neighbor
interface and i'll put you
two neighborly points and then we'll
gain trust and you start measuring
everything it just becomes
mechanic and artificial
it loses its beauty
especially if you track it using
scarcity-based accounting
i think this is one of the binds that
time banks get into because time banks
are really kind of magical in a certain
way
because they what they do is they
have neighbors be able to find each
other for doing these kind of neighborly
services or exchanges like the plumber
you described or or something like that
you know so i can go
mow somebody's lawn and i get time
dollars for that
and they get debited time dollars for
that and then they can whatever
you know maybe i'm doing it for an older
woman in the neighborhood and she bakes
pies that go to somebody else and she
gets earns time dollars for that
but then what happens is when i start
having a relationship with her
because i've mowed her lawn a few times
and she invites me in and serves me
lemonade or whatever then we start
having our own
relationship that we're investing in and
to account for it like
she's getting debited time dollars and
i'm being credited time dollars
no longer feels right for the
relationship
it no longer it's again that mapping the
social frame
right it now now i it's like when you
when you go over to a friend's for
dinner you don't leave a
a 20 bill sitting on the plate right
when you when you get invited over to a
friend's house
for dinner that'd be kind of rude right
because they're not asking you to pay
it was a social occasion and as you
start building that social relationship
if
you still stick with scarcity-based
accounting it puts us
back into really a little bit of a
dehumanized frame
an anti-social frame because that's the
frame that money operates in yes and
so one of the things that struck me uh
when working with the time banks i
worked with the south oregon time banks
for
quite a little time time when i first
arrived to ashland
and um the scarcity mindset
operates even when people are playing
with abundant currencies
so for example when you get into time
banks you you work for someone you
provide some value and you get
time and then it gets accounted to you
but somehow there was the perception
that time points had to be given to the
new person so that they would
feel abundance and it doesn't work that
way
i feel that one of the things that we
need to be shifting is our mindsets of
scarcity
into creating currencies that are not uh
scarce by design but that are actually
pretty dependent because the value that
the community can provide and that i can
provide
uh can be infinite can be full of
of of potential and then the time bank
people i was trying for them to see
that it was not necessary to do that
and but that also they didn't have to
stick with one hour is one hour
of my time regardless if i am a doctor
surgeon and you're you know you're
cleaning my dishes
and and it was not possible to get out
of there because it turns to be an
ideology
more than trying to find a way which we
can create more and more flows
uh for everyone i like that yeah let's
let's dig into this topic some because
this intersects a couple of different
things which i think
are quite interesting we actually have a
time bank in our little town in virginia
stanton virginia called our hour
economy.org and it is the classic
time bank or an hour equals an hour by
ideology
neurosurgeon same as cutting the grass
and we have run into just the things
that you're talking
about that people have a scarcity or
maybe it's a protestant work ethic or
something that
it's good to have a positive balance
right that going
negative is somehow disreputable
and so if we have a community i probably
for
you know psychological or sociological
reasons i don't really
understand the our economy system is
probably over populated with these
diligent reliable people all who
want positive balances and as we know in
a mutual credit system everybody can't
have a positive balance
so we have talked about all these same
things how much startup
credit should people get right i think
that we finally decided on three hours
right
didn't really help any at all because as
you know if you have a mindset that we
all have to be positive you'll
eventually deplete the credit
and things will stop working you know
we've talked about things like
adding a demurrage charge that's one i
still like heavy make it 10
a month right if you accumulate hours
they go away and get redistributed per
capita
again the community was not willing to
go that route again because of
something about hoarding that's good my
positive signal i was a good person
i have a positive balance and you're
absolutely right
if you get away from that perspective it
opens up a vastly bigger space of
opportunity
and you know the whole idea of mutual
credit is an area
that it could be potentially utterly
liberating to
the organization of production
investment and consumption
but it locks down in this scarcity
mindset
i'd love to get your guys thoughts on
that and
you know what if anything can be done is
it currency design like demurrage or
other things or is it more of a
psychological sociological problem of
getting people to realize that
as long as over the long term they're
productive members of society it's
actually a good thing to be negative
because it means
that transactions have occurred i think
it's a big question i'm very interested
in your answers
well for me it has a lot to do with that
frame that i was talking about before
where if you have
this sort of neighborly exchange system
and then
you use scarcity-based accounting as the
frame even if it's mutual credit
and could not be scarce
but the problem is you have a balance
and the way people
have been trained by money which
occupies most of
our imagination when it comes to
currency right because we've
become we've been so buried by our
exposure to money right that
that other things pale in comparison
there is
sort of this shame of having a negative
balance or a fear of having a negative
balance
but if you for example set up a a time
bank that wasn't
a bank but it was more like you set up
the accounting to be in more like a
community service
transcript frame think of it more like
the educational currencies
where you are counting your hours
invested in different types of service
to the community
right nobody has a negative balance they
just have
different periods of time over which
they've invested in the community
right and you can see somebody's time
sheet if you will as as a record
of their service not as a balance
necessarily and i know you know one of
the places that time banks actually
have one of the niches that they've
tried to serve is also like people
coming back
and reintegrating into communities from
prison
because it's very hard for them to get
jobs
but i think something like this
community service
transcript would be much more helpful in
having them
get job placement where they can see
they're an active contributing
citizen that has maybe also a bunch of
testimonials that go along with it
then a time bank balance oh look i've
earned 50 time dollars aren't i great
i like this yeah yeah because that's
open-ended yeah it's all positive i like
that that's very interesting
does the transaction still work so i'm
you know an elderly person who could no
longer shovel their snow
on our time bank you'd put up a request
i'm looking for someone to shovel my
snow
and somebody who felt capable of doing
that would basically take up that offer
do it
and would get no debits or credits but
rather would add
that to their resume shall we say well i
guess that works
it's true you can have kind of the flip
side of that sheet as well which shows
the services i've
i've taken i've accepted right which
also
gives you a sense of is this person in
balance
right like or what kinds of needs they
have
or or things like that right so you can
have both things be visible
i like that a lot because it actually
serves the similar psychological purpose
of dissuading free riders while at the
same time
not being rigorously transaction
oriented and
kind of sucking at her protestant work
ethic towards running up a positive
balance
that's quite interesting because both
are positive in some sense right
either side of the transaction could be
thought of as a positive thing under
that scenario
i think might be worth trying let's move
a little further
again this is an area i'm so interested
in but it's i think
we all know from looking at the history
of people trying it it's really hard to
get it to work
at a large scale our mutual credit
systems
you know there's lots of these little
let systems around there's the weir
system
but again they only seem to work in very
special social contexts
maybe one of you could describe what a
mutual
credit system is and then you know
why haven't these things taken off they
seem like the magic universal solvent
to the problem of money but they just
yet haven't made it
yeah um for me i'm i think i'm a little
bit more precise about my definition of
mutual credit than some people
for me it actually just has to do with
the form of issuance
it means that for every credit created
there is an offsetting debit
that that money is always created
through the act of
an offsetting debit and credit and
therefore what that really means is
all the positive balances always equal
the negative balances
and so the net money supply is always
zero
so this is not how i'm not used to how
we're thinking of money supply
right like if you look at the the
cryptocurrency stuff and all the
you know the coin market cap they're
looking at the supply
as one of the main things and they're
always trying to keep an eye on if the
supply chains then
then this could have value impacts and
all that kind of stuff well the supply
never changes in a mutual credit
currency
and what changes is the active supply
how far people are into the positive or
negative
and so the game in mutual credit as far
as i'm concerned is
the the management of the
credit limit patterns and formulas now
most people like you mentioned time
banks and
let's systems and those kinds of things
most people aren't very creative about
this stuff
there's kind of a vanilla um format
for mutual credit where it's like there
is no formal credit limit and everybody
can go up and down equally and you know
all that kind of thing
and uh as far as i'm concerned that's
that's not very creative and those
things do have a limit on scale and
application that often what you need to
do
is tailor it for a particular use or
need
where you can have different for example
classes of users
that may have different types of credit
limits or different algorithms for
determining their credit limits
and the beauty of this is that if you
have a mutual credit currency
that the supply can be encoded both to
expand when the market needs it when
there's demand for it
and to contract when there's less demand
for it
and fiat currencies suck at contracting
supply
they only know how to devalue when
there's less demand for it
that's actually not quite true let me
probe on this a little bit
because if you think about it using your
definition our current
monetary system is substantially mutual
credit which
seems to me means there may be there's a
problem with the definition
because as we know more than 90 percent
of the money in circulation
is issued by commercial banks under the
fractional reserve
banking regulations or their equivalent
in savings and loans or
credit unions etc and the money does not
have
you know long-term life it only exists
as long as the loan is outstanding
when the loan is repaid that money
literally disappears
now it turns out that because banks are
in the business of lending money
most of the time they recycle the money
back out with new loans as quickly as
they possibly can because the lack of
created money is a lack of profit
opportunity
however one of the things that actually
drives recessions
is when the rate at which new loans are
put out
falls the money supply at least the
locally available money supply actually
falls as well so
our traditional commercial bank driven
fractional reserve banking system has a
lot of those same
attributes so it makes me a little
skeptical of that definition
not exactly here's the thing when a bank
gives me a mortgage right and i they
just created a half a million dollars
or rather they just gave me a check for
a half a million dollars toward paying
off the previous people
right they did not deduct that half a
million dollars
from an account no that's the beauty of
it
you know they love that right buy money
out of thin air but they did give you a
debit
you now have a and actually in their
vocabulary the other way around the
money is a liability to them
but the mortgage is an asset and the two
offset each other
exactly but then what they just did was
doubly create two assets
they created an asset on their books
which is the mortgage of the money that
i own owed them
and they created 500 000 check that they
wrote out to the previous owners to pay
off their mortgage or specifically the
previous owner's bank to pay off the
mortgage right
and uh so you don't have the money being
created with an
offsetting debit and credit let's just
be clear about that from the outset
right so it's being created from nothing
and then the way that they they game
this system is the order of repayment
you know like when use your initial
payments on your
mortgage you've got 99 of it being
applied to interest
and very little of it impacting
principle over time that that switches
right so that
on the on the tail end when you're
finally paying off your home 30 years
later or whatever
it's almost 100 percent of your payment
plan applying to principal
well the reason for that is when you're
repaying principal
that money technically going back out of
circulation
exactly that was my point the money
actually disappears when you repay
principal
so how's that different than mutual
credit because in mutual credit what you
do is
if you create an algorithm for
somebody's credit limit to be tied to
their productive capacity their their
track record rather let's say
so in the case of holofuel it is that
correlated to the past few months of
hosting of hosts
we take that as a strong indicator
of the next few months of hosting of the
likelihood for them to be able to
repay if they go into the negative right
and so your credit limit expands as you
provide value
and as there's demand for that value and
as that
as that demand either decreases or your
ability to provide it decreases
so does your credit limit now that
doesn't necessarily mean
you've changed your balance because many
people may have a credit limit and not
go into the negative at all they may
still have a positive balance or
something like that
but your ability to to draw against that
supply the supply
to draw against changes and so even if
you had a negative balance extended to
your full credit
but your credit credit limit is now
shrinking it means you can't expand it
again you can only contract
as you take in as you take in for
example the hosting payments
they will not be spendable to you
because you're beyond your credit limit
at the moment
does that make sense yeah i guess the
difference
let's see if we can tease out the
difference because there is i can see
there's similarities but there's also
the big difference
is there is not a interest-bearing
liability that's created
in the case of the mutual credit system
nobody is collecting
interest on the money that's been
created
yes that's a big difference but let's
actually i don't want to skip that's not
the biggest difference i don't want to
skip over
fundamentally fiat currency is encoded
for scarcity
what that means is you always owe more
of it
than exists so when i get that half a
million dollar mortgage
over the course of 30 years i'm gonna
have to pay back like three times that
amount depending on the interest rate
that i
that i got it at right i'm gonna have to
pay back 1.5 million
but only a half a million got created
not 1.5 million
so how the heck am i supposed to pay
back 1.5 million on a loan
that only creates a half a million that
can only
happen if i can take it from other
people's principle
because only money that exists was
created
but the money that's owed is the
principal plus interest so for every
dollar created
a dollar plus interest is owed so the
whole system is encoded for scarcity
and also it's unstable unless there's
enough growth
right that's the classic built-in
imperative of growth the fact that we
create the money with a magic wand in
fractional reserve banking but we don't
create the money for the interest and so
if the thing doesn't continue to grow it
runs out of money and crashes
exactly so if we don't grow the economy
next year to service the interest on the
money we issued this year
then we start having massive defaults
and foreclosures and
you know that kind of thing on loans
yeah so a mutual credit let's make sure
we make it clear both
to me would be helpful and to the
audience so in mutual credit
i have good credit say for a thousand
dollars i can create a thousand dollars
worth of money out of thin air
but there's no offsetting interest
generating
liability all i've done is depleted my
credit level i haven't actually
built this liability for interest in the
future is that a fair distinction
i i got a little confused in there as to
which you were talking about because you
said mutual credit but then it sounded
like you were talking about creating it
out of thin air
but you are creating i mean as i
understand mutual credit if i have a
thousand dollar credit limit
i can literally create a thousand
dollars worth of money
out of thin air and all i do i deplete
my
all i can do is spend money in a
transaction right
i don't get to just write a check i
don't get to create some instrument that
has its own independent existence
i can i can participate in a transaction
in which i go into the negative
and somebody else goes into the positive
so really what's
what's happening is somebody else is
providing
value actual real value for
the money they're being credited and i'm
being debited for receiving that value
which is
different than when a bank creates money
from nothing
where they're sending this check and
getting the asset of my mortgage
right and they therefore technically
also get to be the primary owner on my
house
i feel like i want to get into the
different forms of issuance to really
distinguish
what it means to have something created
by fiat literally created by nothing
just the authority to say so
versus something that's asset-backed a
backed currency versus something that's
a mutual credit currency
there they're truly different forms of
issuance and this is i think where
people get really confused
because they only think about money
transactionally
not not about the full life cycle of
issuance
to redemption retirement expiration of
units well dig in they go go for it
because i think i'm confused a little
bit now i thought i understood what
mutual credit was not an area i have a
lot of expertise in but yeah dig into it
let's let's make it as clear as we can
make it
cool so when you have a backed currency
so for example there are some
uh local currencies like berkshires or
there's even
sometimes some local chambers of
commerce create some little currencies
and stuff where they
you you buy local currency units by
spending dollars on them right and
then they can only be spent at these
local businesses and the businesses have
the ability to cash out
for the dollars that are backing the
local credits
that's a backed currency that's actually
backed in this case
by the asset of a dollar now you could
make a currency be backed by electricity
by hosting power by
by different kinds of things right which
is what we do with holofuel it
we really say that it's backed by
hosting power
for the hosts lines of credits
right um and
that's different than when you create
something from nothing there's nothing
on deposit you can't redeem a dollar now
that you said there was a big change in
back in back then there was a gold
standard you could technically redeem a
dollar for gold
you could say that dollars were backed
by gold except the issuance of dollars
wasn't tightly
connected to gold reserve so it was all
very very sloppy
and it was really a bretton woods scheme
to get the
dollar as a universal backing currency
for
so we could kind of tie the whole global
economy together and have everybody use
dollars as a reserve
currency because they knew they could be
redeemed for gold in an emergency
so that that was a a
weird hybrid where it's kind of fiat
currency issuance
with a promise that we're going to
redeem it for something
as long as nobody really calls in that
promise we can get away with that for a
while
and once they started they had to end
the system right exactly
exactly which is why nixon terminated it
in 71 right
so there's asset backed and then there's
what we call
secured where technically what's
happening in the case of a
mortgage is that the mortgage
asset is secured by the house my promise
to pay
is secured by the house now people think
that the 500 000
check that the bank handed me was
secured by the house or is asset backed
but the fact that you can't go and take
those dollars back to the bank and
redeem it from my house
tells you it's not actually backed by it
right
it's it's the loan was secured by it
which basically means technically banks
own almost all the property
in our country not people because we
have them all mortgaged
and and if the bank calls in that
mortgage
they they take the property right during
coronavirus time there's an interesting
thing right where we've
given some flexibility or forgiveness on
payments
but what happens if we cross a threshold
where banks start calling in
all of this stuff right because the
loans the mortgage was secured by the
house
so let me just try again to state them
clearly we've got
fiat issuance created from nothing
we have asset-backed as in the the
currency is redeemable for something we
have secured
issuance which means that the promise
is secured by something that can be
reclaimed which is not the same as a
token holder being able to redeem it
it's a different part of the cycle
and then you have you have weird things
that flip
where is it secured by the issuer or is
it secured by the recipient
right so in the case of the the bank
money
i'm the recipient of the money and i'm
securing the loan it's not that the bank
is securing the loan
i'm securing the loan but that's not
always how it works sometimes the issuer
is also the the person providing the
security
oh sorry there's one other type of
currency and that's a type of currency
that
doesn't really get issued i originally
called it a metacurrency maybe it's
better to be called
a currency constellation but it's
actually one that's computed
or derived from other currencies like
the dow jones index
for example there's now funds that that
you can buy
and trade on the dow jones index but the
dow jones index
is not actually a currency that's issued
it is derived from a series of other
currencies that are issued a bunch of
a bunch of corporate stocks right those
are the different types of
of issuance we didn't quite get all the
way where we wanted to go though because
i did want you to do the same kind of
analysis on mutual credit money
yeah that's the other form of issuance
where
it is created only with an offsetting
debit and credit
right so it can only be done through a
spending type of transaction there are
no
special issuing type of transactions you
could say that the money is being issued
whenever somebody
goes into the negative for any portion
of their transaction
right if i had 20 credits but i'm
spending 50
well 30 just got issued in the process
of me spending that 50.
but the you always have offsetting the
total supply is always zero
which is very much not the way dollars
work the total supply is obviously not
zero then we have in fact we obscure the
total supply right we have the m1 m2
m3 and they stopped publishing the the
larger numbers
because they were shameful i think
at that point the amount of derivation
the amount of derivative
money that we have happening on on top
of the base money
issuance yeah i have a little story
about that which i like to tell people
i might as well tell here yeah which the
fed stopped publishing
m3 in 2006 because it was
seemingly growing at 16 a year
and the economist said that's impossible
right
and guess what it was actually happening
in the form
of very downstream money creation using
a very strange mechanism called
rehypothecation of
collateral where collateral could be
used more than once
in the insides of the banking system
it's very complicated hard to explain
exactly how it works
and so their money was actually
increasing that rapidly
and this is as if the physicists had
decided to
ignore the anomalies detected in the
famous morley mickelson experiments in
the 1880s and 90s
which seemed to show some strange things
about the speed of light if they had
just said forget that
then we would never have had the
breakthrough of einstein
with relativity which was derived from
the fact they did not suppress that
result if the fed had actually taken
seriously this
16 or 18 percent growth in m3 each year
maybe someone would have looked at this
crazy mechanism where
somewhere around six trillion dollars
was manufactured in the united states
over a few year period
and when that money suddenly exploded
downward disappeared in the two weeks
after lehman brothers
that was actually the proximate cause of
what took a medium-sized economic error
giving too many loans to to people who
had bad credit and turned it into a
financial catastrophe it actually had
nothing to do with the mortgages
themselves
rather it had to do with the secondary
effect of the implosion of this
very exotic m3 type money which actually
was being created
so it gives you a warning about what you
choose to ignore
well exactly i mean i think that there's
a real reason for this though
unfortunately
and i ha i am sometimes hesitant to talk
about this i don't want to be
cast as some sort of doom sayer here but
the the reason is that when you have
well that will go back to interest that
you brought up before when you have a
fiat currency
that has compounding interest right
what you end up having is this the money
supply
is forced into this compounding
exponential curve
and the underlying economy is forced to
attempt to match that curve
and the disparity between the economy's
ability to match that curve
and the actual money supply growing
is the likelihood of collapse
essentially right it's like the the it's
showing you how short you're falling
from being able to continue to keep this
plane afloat if you will
right and it's like the warning signals
are going off
that you know that we've got the horizon
line set wrong
and they're choosing to mute the warning
signal
because we're outstripping the ability
for keeping up with that exponential
curve
at this point and so it's better
to mute the warning signal and have
everybody stop panicking
you know is what it seems like like
that's the decision that they're making
and so the question is now when we turn
off
too many things in the dashboard to be
able to actually see
what's happening and what the gap is
then we get blindsided by its
consequences by its effects
and that's you know we're basically
flying blind on some of these things now
yeah we've had all these new means to
paper over the fact that the whole
financial structure is out of whack you
know they keep inventing new
goodies right that was the qes first
right now it's
buying any kind of crappy ass asset and
holding it on the fed's books right yeah
you keep that game going for a while but
i don't think for very long
we'll find out but i want to get back to
um
the different types of currency and in
particular the kind of the asset backing
and what that really looks like when a
currency can be asset backed
you know there are some well there's
futures trading for example right that's
actually backed by the delivery of uh
you know
a container of corn or you know whatever
the thing is at the end of the
the period and until that time people
are trading the futures
on it based on the value that's an
example of kind of a backed
currency but it's a backed currency
optimized for a strange gambling market
right on the on the futures betting well
it's actually good for farmers
farmers use that very legitimately to
lock in the price for their crops
at an appropriate time or they're in the
black i live in an agricultural
area and that's a very important part of
managing your farm is playing the
futures
not playing but using the futures market
appropriately to hedge your crop
right but and it also i mean the
original purpose was to give the farmers
up front liquidity at the beginning of
the growing season when they needed to
be investing the most
so they could basically pre-sell some of
the stuff and get the value up front
and then deliver on their product right
so that it provides an
essential liquidity also to the farmers
but the
the problem as has happened with our
whole economy
and the problem with the futures market
and has happened with our whole economy
is actually
the way i think about it is the tail
wagging the dog what what's happened is
that our whole economy has moved into
where you know i i don't know what the
current number is somewhere around
10 years ago it was around 98 and so
it's probably even higher now with
millisecond trading and everything
but where 98 of the
daily volume of dollars transacted is in
the speculative economy
not in the productive economy and so
you know there was once a time where you
could think of a nation's currency
as being correlated to the productive
capacity of that nation
and that was how currencies were kind of
offset with each other or
valued relative to each other and you
know at this point
it's really all gambling markets it's
all speculation
and the same thing has happened in the
crypto markets in part because there's
so little productive
capacity to to play with in the first
place it's all speculative stuff
and we have the tail wagging the dog and
this is
exactly why we
sorry to bring back to hollow fuel
holochain
you know that kind of stuff why we're
doing some different currency design
patterns
is to bring that center of gravity back
into the
body of the dog if you will back into
the productive capacity
in our case of the hosts providing
hosting power
right or in the case of like joules a
food-backed currency
in the case of the farmers providing
food
or red grids you know internet of
electricity
type currency backed by kilowatt hours
right so
when you bring it back to the ability to
produce
something and have the currency actually
get get tied to
the valuation of the currency get tied
to this asset
it stabilizes currencies again
doesn't it it's not like a stable coin
where it's fixed to a particular
number but it's tied to what it takes to
produce that number what it takes to
grow the food or
provide the hosting power or generate
the electricity
right so you start having a
a more stable center of gravity based
around the productive economy
instead of the tail wagging the dog of
just what speculators are pumping and
dumping
which tend to to largely only benefit
big speculators
right and when other people get caught
in the crosshairs of trying to
participate in the productive economy or
even
small time participate in the
speculative market often
they're on the wrong side of those
curves because they're not the ones
manipulating the market where the
speculators have
their strategies for manipulating the
market and what we've been trying to do
is create a new class of cryptocurrency
that's resilient against
that type of manipulation yeah i like
that
the backed currency idea though of
course it has a limitation which it can
only
at least i haven't seen any proposals
and how it works with non-fungible goods
one of the reasons that mortgages are
the way they are is that every house is
different and nor are they dividable you
can't go and say i want a hundredth of a
house right
you know there's it's a specific house
in a particular place in a specific
condition
etc unlike say electricity or
hollow fuel processing capacity which
one could think at least as
roughly fungible and that you know and
also
approximately fully dividable so it's a
better fit in some ways for a money
system
yeah it's true i mean i think there are
some some things
where i think we can actually also tap
into transportation
and housing but it's housing a little
bit more
a la airbnb than than property ownership
it's like bed nights
room nights if you will you know are a
little bit more of a fungible unit and
they're not not to say that everyone is
equal
but you know there's
a more predictable range and so i
part of my goal really is to have a
series of these things
food energy hosting which is code for
communication and collaboration on all
scales right that's required hosting
in this day and age housing
transportation as we build out that
suite of baseline currencies
it creates the possibility of a whole
other emergent economy
to be built on top of those things if
those things are stabilized
okay this is interesting i'm just trying
to think this through suppose we have
multiple
of these fungible deliverable or
quasi-fungible deliverable
currencies all in operation
simultaneously
how does one exchange amongst them right
one of the great advantages of a neutral
currency like gold
as i swap my wheat for gold and i go buy
eggs with it right
suppose i get you know transportation
miles currency because i
operate a fleet of automated ai vehicles
what can i buy with that how does that
get exchanged for other forms of
currency or get providers to sell me
eggs or you know a new suit or whatever
for my miles based
ai robot car generated currencies or
backed currencies
well realize first of all again that
this provides a base layer like you
could say that when dollars were backed
by gold
people still use dollars for all this
other stuff in fact more people use
dollars for all this other stuff
not because they were ever trading it in
and out of gold but because it provided
a backstop it provided stability for it
for another emergent layer right so when
we look at
holofuel being backed by hosting power
yes there are people who will want to
redeem holofuel for hosting
because they have communication
collaboration tools things that they
want to power
on hosts great but there's also going to
be other things where
i want to run my my airbnb like site and
i want to
i'm going to collect my service fees in
it i want to collect my membership fees
my
subscription fees and then and then it's
going to start expanding out from there
same thing with a currency under you
know with an underlying layer for food
or for electricity right the fact that
you know that it can always
in the end at least be redeemed for
power or for food
right then it means that you can
actually run more stable business models
on it like one of the the challenges
with kind of
sort of stable respectable businesses
getting entangled in the
crypto space is if i accept payment from
my customers in crypto this week
and it drops in value 50 how do i pay my
rent at the end of the month
you know so if you want to make the
space
safe for people to play and build
their more emergent business models on
top of
they can use these currencies just as
that unit of account just like dollars
are used as a unit of account
they don't have to trade miles for
hosting or whatever as if they're going
to use either but
but all it takes is having an account on
both systems to do so
right where i get debited on one system
and credited on another
with my transaction with somebody else
who has an account on both systems
let me have to think that through what
about the fact that at the end of the
day the currency system has to be
careful not to get itself
into a speculative bubble where there's
a lot more
of these currencies running around than
there is the ability to actually deliver
let's say the hosting
if you don't get to that point how does
the amount of currency become
significantly larger than the actual
market for the hosting and hence have
some additional capacity to be able to
use it in these general ways i'm not
sure i see that
well so let's take the the host credit
limit for example
the credit limits don't expand if
there's not a demand for hosting
that's a that's a very tight feedback
loop right because you're
if it's based on your last few months of
of hosting
power if the demand for hosting is
dwindling
then so are the credit limits shrinking
it's a
it's a feedback loop that's very
actually tightly coupled
but if that's the case then how many of
these
posting back currency units will be
available for something other than
buying hosting
so holofuel is a weird example because
i'm such a weird currency geek
holofuel is a hybrid of fiat
backed currency and mutual credit
issuance
the host example where we're talking
about their credit limit
is the standard classic mutual credit
thing where the supply expands and
contracts based on
market behavior and then the the reserve
accounts where you can buy
into holofuel using a cryptocurrency
like hot
tokens or using dollars or euro or
something like that
that's an asset backed scenario where
you have dollars that back the units
that you're buying
and hosts can redeem out for those
dollars
or for those euro or for the the crypto
currency
right and so you only issue credit limit
to that reserve account
as the outside currency is placed on
reserve
so it's a backed currency in that
scenario and then
the ico that we did where we basically
gave an initial line of credit to holo
as the infrastructure provider or
creator
is kind of an active fiat right where
we're saying we're building out this
infrastructure
and we got a large you know
multi-million dollar credit limit
to begin with and now we have to pay
that back over time
but we got this big credit limit to
begin with the accounting is actually
all being done through a mutual credit
currency
but because there's different classes of
accounts with different types of
credit limit algorithms it allows us to
simulate
those behaviors of a fiat a backed and a
mutual credit currency
all in one mutual credit currency
fernando you've been had your hand up
for a while what did you want to add to
the discussion
well you know in and out in and out
because the discussion goes here goes
there
uh but i wanted to give another example
on how we're thinking about jules and
jules
stands for just one organics living
economy system
and just one is a company that produces
beautiful food crystals out of organic
vegetables and fruits that have a very
big shelf life and the mission
of the company is to be able to grow
regenerative soil
and help farmers or by helping farmers
to grow
food so you know part of the design of
jewels which is a constellation of
different currencies
one of them is a coupon which you can
think like oh you know cubans say we see
them everywhere
right and and they're not unusual so
they're easy jewels coupon that you will
be able to
get food with and then get a coupon
and then the incentive is to keep the
coupon for
as long as three years so that then just
when organics can build more capacity
and by doing that you you grow as a
buyer of the coupon
you keep getting a wider percentage of
food
now so we were in that in that design
with the coupons
and we figured oh well it would be great
when people have
10 more food or 20 more food how are we
going to do that with our current
packages which are just 100 grams
and we started to play with how we were
going to do that
and then we started to think well but
that's not the only thing they can
redeem for
because actually people are using the
crystals
to get and produce other foods like like
pixy stix for children or
purest or soups or so there's a whole
production that starts to happen with
that food because you can really create
so many things with it and then we
started to see
how easy it would be to create a whole
marketplace of things that then people
can trade for
within the realm of food so if we start
seeing conventional and then we really
wanted to work like money and we wanted
in the end to be able to trade it for my
ai
whatever or a cell phone well it might
not work
jules might just not be for that just go
and get another currency that would work
for it
and play with the jewels too in the
realm of food
so we create new assets new marketplaces
and new possibilities you know because
the mission
that we have as part of the commons
engine because we do currency design and
we teach currency design
is to be able to provide solutions for
our biggest
challenges not to make people rich or
create a new elite
like it happened with the tokens it's
actually to target
currency into the solution of real
problems
certainly interesting and good if we can
actually do it
what's a good example of a currency
y'all created that's
not use hollow fuel because it sounds
like it's so complicated be very very
hard to deconstruct all the way down but
a simpler example where a currency
design solved a real world problem
i feel like i do a lot of that but this
is in the domain of
currencies that people don't necessarily
always think of as
currency and i want to give an example
that i
that i like where i was trying to
encourage people to solve a real world
problem it's just a very vivid example i
think that
unfortunately they didn't use it but
it's still i think a worthwhile example
because it's so obvious to see how it
solves the problem
at occupy wall street they had this
reinventing money work group
that uh you know wanted to create some
sort of occupy dollar so they could
actually like
pay the people that were contributing
various things
food and you know um sleeping bags
and stuff like that in these in these
occupy bucks and
they came to us we're talking about this
i'm like are you having a problem with
those flows
right now they're like well no
everything's going really great i'm like
why would you want to insert a currency
into it why would you want to
put something in place that's designed
to shit to change the pattern of flows
in a pattern of flows that's working
right let's take a pattern of flows that
isn't working let's take a real world
problem that you want to solve
that's going on there's well for example
we've got we have problems sleeping you
know the police often just send people
down here when they're getting
released from jail saying hey there's
free food and tents and sleeping bags
down at zuccotti square
go on down there and and those people
aren't always here for the same reasons
as us and they don't always follow
our rules about like quiet time after 10
p.m
or no substance use and and things like
that and then
for those of us that actually have jobs
and have to work but we're still
staying down here and that kind of thing
we end up not being able to sleep and
like well you're not able to address
that in the general assembly and
like no because it's it keeps being
turned into a personal
issue you know and it's harder to see
the overall pattern i'm like great okay
cool
so uh and i think actually eric harris
brown came up with the first part of
this is it's like
what what happens in the morning where
can we get this feedback and make it
visible to everyone well
there's a breakfast line and you can
have everybody as they get in the
breakfast line give them
a coffee bean and have three jars
with a green yellow red lid if you will
or
tape on them or whatever ideally they'd
be narrow in tall jars
and they drop their coffee bean in the
jar
appropriate to whether they got great
sleep green
horrible not enough sleep red or
somewhere not so great but in the middle
you know yellow and it's just every day
you can actually have the community
see the health of the community from the
sleep
right from how tall which jars you know
get stacked up inside of there right
so this is sort of like a reputation
currency it has limited
issuance for the you know you getting in
the in the breakfast line
but it it it's more reliable than like
going around and doing
some kind of survey because of sampling
bias and all that other kind of stuff
and it's you don't even have to count it
it's kind of a non-numerical currency if
you
just make the jars the right kind of
shape you can see the levels you're
you're just eyeballing what is the
health of the community here
not very many people are getting good
sleep or whatever we're solving a very
practical human need with a currency
ability to see the flow
of sleep that's a very interesting
example actually
and they didn't choose to do that no
they're like that's not a money monetary
currency where the reinventing money
group i'm like
you said you wanted to solve a problem
you told me a problem
we came up with a currency that solves
it you know like
clever clever let's let's actually talk
about this something we talked a little
bit about offline
before we got started is that you have
done some thinking about non-numeric
currencies and there was a good example
how would you distinguish a non-numeric
from the numeric currencies and
what are some other examples or what
kind of classes of problems would
non-numeric currencies be useful for
well i think it's really important to
recognize different
forms of formalization when you're
building a currency
so i can't think of his first name
somebody stevens howard stevens maybe
a social scientist put in place these
different
methods of metrics used in social
sciences it's you know in the
in the physical sciences it's it's easy
to make everything
fully quantitative often right
not always true but it's generally
easier to make things fully quantitative
in the in the
social sciences it's not always as easy
to make them quantitative in the same
way
so what he introduced was these
different types of things of you have
rational numbers
things that actually can be divided into
parts have ratios of things
you have interval or integral numbers
integers whole numbers
you have ordinal numbers rankings of
things
and you have nominal you would not call
them numbers you'd have nominal
categories names for things
and what's what's really interesting is
you can make currencies
embody any of these kinds of patterns
like typically
most good reputation currencies steer
very far away from the rational end of
of that spectrum if you will right you
say you have a
you know a bachelor's of science in this
or a phd
in this that's a nominal currency right
that's
that's the name of a particular level
and then you even might
might also name the issuer you know from
harvard university
or you know whatever if you also want to
ride on the nominal
status of that university and we use
jobs and titles
for the same thing right ceo or
you know like these are these are
nominal currencies that
carry a bunch of reputational signals in
them
they're not numeric and what's what's
interesting is
how you can design currencies to
resonate
with different audiences based on how
you formalize them
and you may have initially collected
some numeric data
right your grades and test scores
and your credits right your grades and
test scores may have been
rational numbers your credits were
interval integral numbers integers whole
numbers
but then you get a degree that's issued
in the form of a nominal currency
so if you're creating reputation systems
on a
you know a website an online community
or something like that often what you
want to do
is not have the reputation be a number
at all
you want to have it be a name that
you've achieved this level of
citizenship or this type of helper or
this type of mentor
this type of you know whatever the
different kinds of things are
and you embody the values
of the community and and the kind of
appreciation of the community in the
naming
of those levels right and
it makes all the difference in the world
how you encode these things
we could get into a whole other spiral
dynamics conversations about the sort of
the different
colors of memes that the different
formalizations resonate with
we all have had so much experience of
being dehumanized
by money by these rational numbers you
are dealing with green mean people that
are trying to sort of re-humanize
and build you know communitarian types
of values into things
and you bring a currency system to them
that's all about these rational numbers
or even rankings in social status you're
going to repel
people from participating what you want
to do in that scenario is have
whole numbers of contributions and
named levels of participation
name types of participation that type of
thing and that resonates very strongly
with the green meme
got a whole map around these kinds of
things for when you're designing
currencies
who's your audience and how do you
design make it make sure your design
actually maps to the right social frame
like we were originally talking about
around reputation currencies and such or
any type of currencies
the further you go from the social frame
of who you're trying to have participate
the more cognitive overhead
there is and anyway there's a lot of a
lot of work there
for that and then you can solve very
concrete real world problems with this
you know like went into a school a small
private school that had
had basically collapsed all the staff
quit two weeks before school
it started and i stepped in as the
temporary executive director
and turned manhattan free school around
into an agile learning center
and agile learning centers then took off
and have grown to last i checked about
like 92 schools all over the world
but it was all through these types of
current seas
setting up the feedback loops so that
the community could see themselves and
manage themselves more effectively
okay very interesting you know again
some of it's back to the past as we
talked about you know the medieval guild
systems had all kinds of intricate ranks
and none of it was numeric of course in
those days it had to do with
items of dress that you were allowed to
wear the sumptuary laws you know
depending on where you were in the
social system
you were allowed to wear lace or you
were not or you were allowed to have
buckles on your shoes or you were
not these are you know highly analog
signaling system so your and your
hypothesis is that
people who are in the post-modern epoch
are more likely to react well to these
kind of analog signals as opposed to
digital signals
is that part of your hypothesis
well analog and digital doesn't quite
map because
obviously many of these things are still
coming through digital media
right but it's not quantitative it's not
numeric right when you're wearing
the dress of the
you know carpenter with the two zippers
down the front of your pants and you
know
you know that that kind of thing it it's
sending a particular visual signal
it's providing cues for what
role you play in the community
right and so you still need signaling
systems for those cues
but numbers are not necessarily the best
signals
in fact numbers are kind of horrible
signals so i can give you an example of
that if you want
sure and that's something that i would
like to see designed
for organizations and communities could
do the same
so let's say that you wanted to see what
is the morale or
what is the what is the um energetics of
people
in a given field you know within an
organization to set this example
and you know people come sometimes
stress or sometimes they're flowing and
happy
and you don't get to know that but how
they come unless you ask them hey how
you feel today what's up for you what's
new for you what's
but what if we would have like a way in
which people could have like a color
spectrum like a rainbow type and you
know we
just decide the value of each of these
colors
and let's say that red is when we're
really stressed
and you know like yellow is when we're
really happy and centered
and then people come and they just
choose a color in the day
and then you see a dashboard of what's
going on with the organization in the in
the
middle of the day and you get a sense
and sometimes you know as
working in organizational architecture i
can tell you would be so valuable
because
it provides a sensing for me as
a person in hr or a person in community
building to be able to know
what is happening fast without having to
go to
asks people and if sometimes is red
maybe it's accurate even to what was
matching my own personal sense of oh
today's a red day
of course we just started the covet
everybody sent home they didn't really
know
of course we're red i don't have to do
anything about it but
you know another given date could be
like oh payroll just happened and it's
red i wonder if there's something else
happening that i need to ask about
and but you get an immediate uh in
collective intelligence we say the word
collapticism you get
a whole optical view right like a
sense of the whole we need a dashboard
that provides you certain colors of a
spectrum
that's interesting i think we're about
out of time here
about to wrap up but i will ask one
question that
maybe teases at this a little bit if we
think about
what's probably the most powerful
reputation system at least that i'm
aware of in the united states maybe the
world
it's the amazon star rating system
people pay a lot of attention to that it
actually kind of works
and it's interesting that it is both
analog
and digital in some sense right you rank
one to five stars or integer and real
number at the same time
and yet the resultant thing that i think
we all tend to work on
is some estimated real number average
number of stars
they also do clever things like show you
other dimensions like they'll actually
show you the histogram if you know how
to get to it etc
how does the amazon star rating system
fit into your design space
well frankly i think it's a little poor
uh it's not dimensional enough there's a
whole thing
i wrote up once about this actually
regarding the ebay rating system
that exists it's like if you're trying
to figure out what it is that a buyer
needs
to know they're like yeah there's the
quality of the product there's quality
of communication if there's a problem
and sorting out things there's the speed
of delivery
right now amazon's gotten the speed of
delivery down a lot and they try to
give you that information in the in the
checkout process anyway
but this is originally for for ebay that
i'm talking about
and you want all these things to be
different dimensions you don't want to
just give a plus one or minus one
right you you actually need to give the
person dimensionality so that they can
make smarter decisions
in fact i would diverge from your
example of
amazon as maybe the most influential
thing and i would look for example that
olympic gold medals or olympic medals
just
you know when you consider that they
shape the participation of millions of
athletes in every country all
over the world and then there's all the
subsidiary currencies
that are involved in the score making
that allow somebody to get into the
olympics that allows them to win a medal
the medals are just an ordinal currency
they're just first second third they're
called
you know gold silver bronze but it's not
because of
you the value you can melt them down for
that they have value
it's because of the reputation that they
have value right and there's such an
intricate rich system of dimensional
currencies where every sport has its own
set of currencies now they still come
down to a gold medal
did you come in first second or third
they're still coming down to your
ranking
but you know the things used in diving
and gymnastics
you know for versus in you know um
shooting and decathlon and you know
basketball or
you know there's very different measures
and metrics used in each one of these
and yet they are the things that measure
the flow that occurred
and are the indicator of the excellence
of the athlete
so we've got we've created this super
complex
currency system that goes in behind
these olympic medals and look at how
millions
how many millions of people's behavior
that they shape
what doesn't strike me doesn't have any
influence on me as far as i can tell so
i probably don't
think of it but i can see your point
well i think on that point we will
wrap her up we've been going at it here
for a good period of time we've covered
a tremendous amount of ground
[Music]
production services and audio editing by
jared janes consulting
music by tom muller at
modernspacemusic.com